Guide to the Stanley Postek Spanish Civil War Papers ALBA.089
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Stanley Postek Spanish Civil War Papers
1934-1989, (Bulk 1937-1939)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Postek, Stanley, 1912-1991
ALBA.089
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Stanley Postek (1912-1991) was a sailor, prizefighter and union organizer who went to Spain in 1938 to fight in the Spanish Civil War. After being seriously injured, Postek was detained in a concentration camp in France before returning to New York. Postek later served in World War II as a merchant seaman. The collection consists of materials, including personal journals, from Postek's time in Spain and afterward and from his period of service as a merchant marine in World War II. Later papers include newspaper articles and other writings about aspects of the Spanish Civil War, memorial items about veterans, and material documenting Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) activities.
Provenance
The Stanley Postek Collection was donated to Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives in the early 1990s by Postek's daughter, Judi Darnell. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Born Ladislaus Ferdinand Szeliga in 1912 in Lowell, Massachusetts, Stanley Postek adopted his cousin's name when he ran away from home as a teenager. He left school in the mid-thirties to become a sailor and union organizer for the International Seamen's Union of America, and a founding member of the breakaway National Maritime Union. In 1937 Postek became a light heavyweight boxing champion. In May 1938, he sailed to Europe to join the International Brigades in the Spanish Civil War.
In Spain Postek was initially assigned to the Canadian Mackenzie-Papineau Battalion, and subsequently transferred to a machine-gun company of the Abraham Lincoln Battalion. He was seriously injured in August 1938. When the International Brigades were evacuated that November, Postek, who was in a hospital, was left behind. In January 1939, he walked over the border into France and was immediately detained in the Argeles-sur-Mer concentration camp, where he almost died of septicemia. A week later, Postek managed to escape from the camp with the help of a journalist from the Paris Herald Tribune. Without a passport or any identification, Postek spent a period of rehabilitation in a Paris hospital, and finally returned to New York as a stowaway in May 1939.
Postek served in World War II as a merchant seaman, most notably on the Murmansk Run. After the war, he joined the International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union. He was one of 2,000 seamen barred from employment by the Coast Guard during the Korean War for his association with the Communist Party. Postek later worked as an extra in the entertainment business, notably as a longshoreman in the Elia Kazan film, "On the Waterfront." After he retired, Postek worked with the Marine Worker's Historical Association, as well as teaching several college courses. In the 1960s he ran a successful macramé shop in Greenwich Village, the Rope Gallery, adapting his sailor's knot-tying expertise to a new craft.
Postek died in 1991 at his home in San Diego, California.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Spanish Civil War Era and World War II, 1934-1946 contains materials from Postek's time in Spain and afterward, as well as from his period of service as a merchant marine in World War II. Includes military and political identification cards and books, stamps and other memorabilia from Spain, and a letter of permission to leave the Argeles-sur-mer concentration camp.
Series II: Journals, 1939-1988, consists of Postek's handwritten "Memoirs of Spain" begun in March 1939 while recuperating in a hospital in Paris. The journal, which includes a sketch Postek made of himself in a torso cast, begins as an attempt to give a detailed account of his experiences in Spain, and evolves into a journal of his encounters with women and life aboard various ships on which he was working. Also noteworthy in this series is a journal Postek kept during his service on the Murmansk Run during World War II.
Series III: Subject Files, 1952-1989, consists of newspaper articles about Spain and Spanish Civil War veterans, and scholarly and other writings about aspects of the Spanish Civil War; poetry and memorial items about veterans; lists of maritime members of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB), as well as other VALB documents, ephemera and correspondence.
Arrangement
Series I and III are arranged alphabetically. Series II is arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into three series:
Missing Title
I, Spanish Civil War Era and World War II, 1934-1946
II, Journals, 1939-1988
III, Subject Files, 1952-1989
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Stanley Postek interview, in the Manny Harriman Video Oral History Collection (ALBA VIDEO 48)
Marine Workers Historical Collection (TAM 125)
Stanley Postek Papers (WAG 080)
Stanley Postek Photographs (ALBA PHOTO 089)
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Photographs from the Spanish Civil War and later, as well as videotapes of a memorial service for Spanish Civil War veteran Eliseo Del Rio from the Stanley Postek Collection have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection at the Tamiment Library.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Personal papers.; Memorabilia.; Diaries; Articles.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Postek, Stanley, 1912-1991; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV--Biography; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion
- Series I: Spanish Civil War Era and World War II, 1934-1946
  - Bailey, William: article by, letter from, ca.1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, undated, 1934-1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter of permission to leave concentration camp, Feb 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memorabilia: Stamps, metro tickets, boarding pass, uniform patches, flyer, undated, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Military, political and hospital identifications, passbooks, merit award, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Poems and lyrics, undated, Jan 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Postek, Stanley: Articles and poem about, undated, 1937, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Postek, Stanley: Voucher letters for, Apr 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Membership cards and convention pass, 1939, 1942, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Volunteer for Liberty (British), 1944 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II. Journals, 1939-1988
  - Postek, Stanley: Journal, "Memoirs of Spain", Mar 1939-Feb 1942, 1964, 1982-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Postek, Stanley: Journal, Jul 1942-Dec 1942 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Postek, Stanley: Journal, undated, Mar 1943-Apr 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series III: Subject Files, 1952-1989
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Certificate of Honor, Jan 1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings: Spain politics, Apr 1983-Jan 1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - For Valor in Battle (pamphlet by Joseph North), Apr 1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Good Fight: Film reviews, promotional material, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Heroines of the Good Fight: North American Women Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War (article by Frances Patai), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Oral History of the American Left (newsletter), Apr 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - O'Toole, Lawrence: Notes from audiotape interview with; obituaries and tributes, undated, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Point of Clarification: Postek's response to Joe Doyle's "Seamen in the Lincoln Battalion", ca.1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Postcard, flyer, calling card, Mexican tourist visa, undated, 1963, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Postek, Stanley: Film headshot/resumé, ca.1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Postek, Stanley: Narrative of Spanish Civil War injury, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Seamen in the Lincoln Battalion (article by Joe Doyle), Feb 1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Spanish Civil War Historical Society, undated, Mar 1982 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Tom Paine Brigade: Anti-Stalinist flyer, ca.1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - True Americans (article by Roy Hudson), Aug 1979 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - U.S. Political Culture of the 1930s and the American Response to the Spanish Civil War (article by Robert Colodny), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Veterans: Articles, obituaries, poems, testimonials by and about, undated, 1975-1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Veterans: Return visits to Spain, undated, 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Anniversary reservation, Congressional citation, 1978, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Bibliography, newsletter, Congressional amendment proposal, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Correspondence, Dec 1977, Sep 1989 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Maritime veterans, undated, Jun 1979-Apr 1984 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Veterans lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)